<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>His Majesty the King of Denmarks letter to His Highness the Duke of Holstein (Gottorp) concerning the sequestration of the Dukedom of Schleswig and the said Dukes answer thereunto : as also His Imperial Majesties letter to the Duke of Holstein, with the Duke's answer.</title>
            <author>Christian V, King of Denmark and Norway, 1646-1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A32886</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3936A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26462</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09475223</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09475223</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43219</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A32886)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43219)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1305:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>His Majesty the King of Denmarks letter to His Highness the Duke of Holstein (Gottorp) concerning the sequestration of the Dukedom of Schleswig and the said Dukes answer thereunto : as also His Imperial Majesties letter to the Duke of Holstein, with the Duke's answer.</title>
                  <author>Christian V, King of Denmark and Norway, 1646-1699.</author>
                  <author>Leopold I, Holy Roman Emperor, 1640-1705.</author>
                  <author>Christian Albrecht, Duke of Holstein-Gottorp, 1641-1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>23 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Denmark --  History --  Christian V, 1670-1699.</term>
               <term>Schleswig-Holstein (Germany) --  History.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43219:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43219:1"/>
            <p>His MAJESTY the <hi>King of Denmarks</hi> LETTER To His HIGHNESS the <hi>Duke of Holſtein <hi>(GOTTORP)</hi>
               </hi> Concerning the Sequeſtration of the <hi>Dukedom</hi> of <hi>Schleſwig:</hi> And the ſaid Duke's Anſwer thereunto.</p>
            <p>As alſo His <hi>Imperial Majeſties</hi> Letter to the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Holſtein:</hi> With the <hi>Dukes</hi> Anſwer.</p>
            <p>Printed <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1677.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:43219:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:43219:2"/>
            <head>THE KING of <hi>DENMARK</hi>s LETTER to the DUKE of <hi>HOLSTEIN Gottorp,</hi> Concerning the SEQUESTRATION.</head>
            <head>
               <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the Fifth, by the Grace of God, King of <hi>Denmark, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Serene Duke, &amp;c.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is not unknown to your Dilection, what hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hath paſt about the receiving of the Inveſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture over the Dukedom of <hi>Schleſwig;</hi> whereunto you have obliged your ſelf by the late Agreement of <hi>Rendesbourg;</hi> and how your Dilection ſince that time, upon our ſeveral well-minded Admonitions, by divers Letters directed to Us, hath promiſed the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance thereof; and in order thereunto, ſent hither ſome of your Miniſters, who nevertheleſs under the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43219:3"/>pretext of going for ſome nearer inſtructions from your Dilection, are lately parted again from hence, without having diſpatched any thing at all. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as We have hitherto in vain expected their promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed return; the time likewiſe at the ſaid Agreement of <hi>Rendesbourg</hi> appointed for the receiving of the above-mentioned Inveſtiture being already in the Month of.<hi>July</hi> laſt paſt, beſides divers others ſince indulged Terms long ago expired; We alſo having a ſufficient and true information of thoſe moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Machinations, which your Dilection hath in hand againſt Us and Our State; and beſides, being very requiſite, that We carefully do mind what is neceſſary for the preſerving of this Inveſtiture, depending from Us and Our Crown of <hi>Denmark:</hi> Therefore have we found Our ſelves unavoidably, and as it were againſt Our will obliged, now to Sequeſtrate that part of the ſaid Dukedom, wherewith your Dilections Anceſtors have been heretofore Inveſted; and to iſſue out a Commiſſion to ſome of our Councellors and Officers there reſiding, for putting in Execution the ſaid Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtration, and for performing all what is neceſſary to be done about the ſame. Since therefore We would rather have deſired any thing elſe, than to come to this Extremity, We have thought good to give no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of this Our Reſolution to your Dilection, and to appoint yet out of a ſuper-abundance another Term of Six weeks from the date hereof, for the receiving of the ſaid Inveſtiture, to the end that your Dilection and all the World may ſee, how willingly We would uſe all poſſible moderation herein, without any over-haſtening of your Dilection. However, we do it with
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43219:3"/>this further precaution and warning, that in caſe the ſaid prefixed Term, contrary to all expectation, like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſhould be diſregarded by your Dilection, We then ſhall be neceſſitated, though much againſt Our Will, to proceed <hi>ad apſam Pravationem Feudi,</hi> or to the cutting off the <hi>Fief,</hi> and to take ſuch further courſes as the <hi>Feudal Laws</hi> do allow of. Of all this We have thought convenient to advertiſe your Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, Recommending, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Dated at Our Place of Reſidence at <hi>Copenhagen,</hi> 
                  <date>the 19th of <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1676.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Dilections Affectionate Couſen and Brother-in-Law, <hi>CHRISTIAN.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:43219:4"/>
            <head>The Duke of <hi>HOLSTEIN</hi>'s Anſwer to the aforegoing Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Moſt Serene and moſt Potent King,</hi> &amp;c.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOur Majeſties Letter of the 19th of <hi>December</hi> laſt paſt, from <hi>Copenhagen</hi> directed to Us, hath been preſented to Our hands the ſecond of this inſtant, by an Expreſs from one of your Majeſties Commiſſaries; By the Contents whereof We have ſeen the ſame, what already ſome days before had been publiſhed by ſome Letters Pattents affix'd in Our Dukedom of <hi>Schleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wig, viz.</hi> That your Majeſty hath been induced to Sequeſtrate that part of the ſaid Dukedom, which doth belong to Us, and to nominate to that effect certain Commiſſaries, with the annexed warning, that in caſe we did not within Six weeks, from the date of the ſaid Letter, effectually accompliſh the receiving of the Invenſtiture over that Dukedom of <hi>Schleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wig,</hi> your Majeſty would proceed <hi>ad ipſam Priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem Feudi,</hi> or the cutting off the Fief, and take ſuch further courſes as the <hi>Feudal Laws</hi> do allow off, being moved thereunto by theſe reaſons, That We in the point of the receiving of the ſaid Inveſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, neither had performed that ſo termed late A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement of <hi>Rendesbourgh,</hi> nor the Promiſes made by Our Letters under Our own hand, nor ſent back our Miniſters, who without any diſpatch of Affairs
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43219:4"/>were gone from <hi>Copenhagen;</hi> but that on the contrary we had had in hand moſt dangerous, and by a ſingular accident, diſcovered machinations againſt your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and your State; and had alſo, as it were, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidably obliged your Majeſty to the preſervation of your Majeſties and the Crown of <hi>Denmark</hi>'s own Rights.</p>
            <p>Whereupon we cannot but with all due reſpect re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn this our Anſwer to your Majeſty, that for the ſake of your Majeſty's own Glory, and high Reputation, and your Realms and Dominions welfare, We have moſt ardently deſired and wiſhed, that our thoughts at the firſt ſeeing of your Majeſty's afore-mentioned Letters Patents, (as if they might have been publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without your knowledg) might have a ſure ground, and your Majeſty ſuch a Kindneſs for us, as not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge any longer our Perſecutors, but rather to put a period to thoſe unuſual hard proceedings, which we undeſervedly have ſuffered from them, and to reeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh and conſolidate that ancient tie and friendſhip which hath proved ſo uſeful and beneficial to both Great Houſes, and their reſpective Kingdoms, Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories and Subjects; ſeriouſly conſidering withal, that it cannot be available neither to the repute of your Majeſty's innate Generoſity, nor to your Majeſty's Realms and Dominions, to ſee us, who are in many regards ſo nearly related, and never failing neither in due Reſpects, nor required Faithfulneſs to your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, thus oppreſſed, and reduced to a quite deſperate condition, without having been able to impetrate the leaſt redreſs, which yet lies ſo abſolutely in your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's own hands.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:43219:5"/>
            <p>However, this is our only and eſpecial comfort in all our daily increaſing calamities, that your Majeſty by your Letters doth ſuppeditate to us an occaſion to make our juſtification before your ſelf and briefly to refute thoſe accuſations ſo inhumanly invented by our ill-willers. For your Majeſty's own Chriſtian Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience will be the beſt and ſureſt witneſs for us, that we never have entertained any other Counſels, nor have negotiated with any body whatſoever about any other things, but what to our beſt underſtanding we have deemed to be good, expedient and lawful for a free Prince, to preſerve our ſelves in that State God Almighty hath been pleaſed to ſettle us in, by making us a lawful Heir and Succeſſor to the Duke our Father of bleſſed memory, and to tranſmit the ſame to our Poſterity, even as we had got it. We our ſelves have not made that Agreement concluded at <hi>Copenhagen</hi> on the 12th. day of <hi>May</hi> in the year 1658, but have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herited thoſe Rights, which in due conſideration of the manifold damages ſuſtained, were thereby accrued to our Family. And it is alſo known to the World, that we have employed none at all at the Treaty and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of the reiterated Northern Peace in the Camp for <hi>Copenhagen,</hi> on the 27th. day of <hi>May</hi> in the year 1660, although we had then already taken the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon us; and the ſaid Treaty of <hi>Copenhagen</hi> hath nevertheleſs been confirmed therein, and the <hi>Gua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantie</hi> thereof undertaken by them three moſt Puiſſant States of Chriſtendom: And preſuppoſed his Majeſty the King of <hi>Denmark, Frederick</hi> the Third, our moſt Honoured Father-in-Law of glorious memory, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing unwillingly, and againſt his mind, (which yet is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43219:5"/>altogether unknown to us, ſince his Family as well as ours hath been benefitted thereby,) ſhould have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded to the granting of that Sovereignty, and other advantages promiſed to our Family; however it is but a meerly ſpontaneous Act: Nay, it hath been an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent token of his Royal Affection towards us, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving obſerved by our Addreſſes for a near Alliance of Marriage in his Royal Family, our ſincere inclination towards him, his Majeſty in the year 1667; when the Contract of Marriage in his own Fortreſs at <hi>Gluck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtadi</hi> was a making up, hath in all and the ſingular Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, Points and Clauſes, wholly, and to all perpetuity, confirmed to us the above-ſaid Treaty of <hi>Copenhagen,</hi> grounded upon the Sovereignty over the Dukedom of <hi>Schleſwig,</hi> and eſtabliſhed the ſame jointly with that ancient Union for a perpetual norm and rule betwixt both Families, with this engagement, and Royal firm Parol, that himſelf and his hereditary Succeſſors in the Government, neither directly nor indirectly would act, nor cauſe to be acted againſt the ſame. But in what manner we have ſince been dealt withal at <hi>Rendenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg</hi> in the year 1675. and how we have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained by a moſt troubleſome detention to ſurrender our Fortreſſes, Artillery, Ammunition and Militia; yet with this Comfort given us, that all differences there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with were ended, and upon change of Times, and an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Peace, all ſhould be reſtored in ſuch a condition as it was taken from us; and how notwithſtanding all this, (after we forſooth for our Perſon were diſmiſſed to <hi>Gottorp,</hi> yet ſtill had ſtrange Troops about us, and ſo only had changed place, but not detention,) certain Articles have been preſcribed to our Miniſters and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43219:6"/>Counſellors remaining behind in Arreſt, and we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to the pretended Ratification thereof, even as we were to the ſurrender of our Fortreſſes without any liberty left us, only therin to alter things quite in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with the Dignity of a Free-<hi>German</hi> Prince of the Empire: We are as unwilling to relate, as your Majeſty can be deſirous to hear, and ſhould alſo have forborn to mention it either to your Majeſty, or to any others, if we were not aſſured in our Conſcience that your Majeſty out of an inbred He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick love to Juſtice doth deteſt ſuch a way of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, and in that regard hath laid a Ground for that high diſpleaſure your Majeſty thereupon conceived againſt him, who out of Reaſons unknown to us, hath occaſioned all that miſchief which then did befall us.</p>
            <p>And ſince thar time we have not been able to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, that your Majeſty ſhould ever have intended, to erect that ſo termed Agreement of <hi>Rendesbourg,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from ſuch derogatory and extorted Principles, and conſequently turning void by Law, into a <hi>Prag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical Sanction,</hi> after your Majeſty hath charged our Subjects with ſuch Contributions as are untolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and do quite cut of both our extraordinary and ordinary Revenues, and hath quite demoliſhed to the Ground our Fortreſſes, your Majeſty having thus your ſelf thereby introduced an impoſſibility to perform what the pretended Agreement of <hi>Rendesbourg</hi> doth import; For if we by virtue thereof are to receive the Inveſtiture over the Dukedom of <hi>Schleſwig,</hi> it muſt be done at leaſt after ſuch a manner, as the Duke our Father of bleſſed Memory the laſt time,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43219:6"/>
               <hi>viz.</hi> In the year 1648, hath received the ſame; and then we ought to be inveſted not only with the bare Land, but alſo with thoſe Fortreſſes, fince the laſt Feudal Letter doth make expreſs mention thereof. It is true, we do confeſs, that even after ſuch rigorous proceedings, to teſtify our deference to your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and our deſire to Peace, but chiefly, to ſuble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate ſomething our Subjects groaning under their bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and to promote their freedom according to our Power; we have been come ſo far, as to condeſcend at length to the receiving the Inveſtiture upon theſe terms, that all things ſhould be reſettled in ſuch a ſtate, as they had been before the pretended Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Rendesbourg,</hi> and that the weighty burthen lying upon our Territories, ſhould be taken off, and due ſatisfaction effectually made for the dammages ſuſtained: And for that purpoſe we have ſent ſome of our Miniſters to <hi>Copenhagen;</hi> but our juſt deſires have been rejected, an unconditional performance of the Feudal Duty inſiſted on, and the redreſs of our Grievances ſet out of doors, and our Miniſters ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving alleadged the want of full Powers thereunto, have been ſent away back for new Inſtructions; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being recalled by us from <hi>Copenhagen,</hi> as Her Majeſty the Queen Mother by her own Letters dated at <hi>Copenhagen</hi> the 19th day of <hi>November,</hi> 1676, hath informed us. And we do confeſs very freely, that in caſe our Subjects preſently after our Conditional Promiſe made, had been eaſed from their burthen, the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſes reduced to their former ſtate, and due ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction effectually given us, we would have done the utmoſt, and undergone afreſh that Feudal Duty.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43219:7"/>But whereas alſo yet fince poſſeſſion hath been taken, of our part of <hi>Stadt</hi> and <hi>Butjadinger-Land,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the ſame hath no relation at all to that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, which was actitated at <hi>Vienna</hi> in the Cauſe of <hi>Oldenbourg,</hi> and beſides his deſcending as a Fief from the Ducal Houſe of <hi>Brunſwig Lunebourg.</hi> Our Subjects likewiſe both in <hi>Holſtein</hi> and <hi>Sleſwig</hi> have been forbid to pay us the few remaining ordinary dues, and furthermore ſuch aims are made, as to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude us from that Treaty of a General Peace at <hi>Nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vegen,</hi> and conſequently from all hopes of redreſs, and yet hath but lately the Navigation been by open Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations abſolutely Interdicted to all our Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants and Subjects of the Dukedoms of <hi>Schleſwig</hi> and <hi>Holſtein,</hi> without affording us, as Prince Regent, the leaſt communication thereof, much leſs deſigning us to joyn in the ſaid Publication, if the ſame had been required: We therefore have had good reaſon to wave the ſending over our Deputies the ſecond time again, after they were thus diſmiſſed before, but rather have taken a firm reſolution to get our Cauſe ventilated and diſcuſſed at the Treaty of the General Peace at <hi>Nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wegen,</hi> with theſe certain hopes and confidence, that no Potentate concerned therein will diſpute our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, in regard that amongſt other high concerns, there will be alſo treated about the re-eſtabliſhment of the Northern Peace, whereupon our Sovreignty over the Dukedom of <hi>Sbhleſwig</hi> with the other ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages ſtipulated for us and our Family, is not only grounded, but alſo is an eſſential part thereof and ſtands comprehended under the undertaken Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral and Special Warranty. Neither do we think.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43219:7"/>that your Majeſties Miniſter in <hi>Holland</hi> hath had any orders to render difficult the impetrating of the Paſports, by us deſired from the <hi>States General</hi> of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited-Provinces;</hi> for our Miniſters deſtined to <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megen,</hi> ſeeing he hath not been able to alledg any thing at all which ſhould deſerve the leaſt reflexion, and exclude us from the General-Treaty, if we were but to be conſidered as a <hi>German</hi> Prince, and had no concerns in the re-eſtabliſhment of the Northern Peace, which nevertheleſs hath firſt of all periclitated on our ſide. But concerning thoſe machinations di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcovered by a ſingular accident, whereby, as we do conceive, ſome end<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>vours are uſed, to juſtify that in all points disformally commenced Sequeſtration, we have not the leaſt cauſe to clear our ſelves in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, before any particulars are nearer touched, and it be duly made appear to us, that we have been given concerned in any of thoſe Machinations repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to your Majeſty. However we are ſure and confident, that we never have been ſo ſuſpectedly privy to any thing, as that thereby juſt cauſe ſhould have been given, to charge us therewith by Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates both within and without the Empire, and to abalienate their former inclination from us and our Family, much leſs can a Pretext thereby conveniently be taken to ſequeſtrate that part of the Dukedom of <hi>Schleſwig,</hi> which with all right Hereditarily and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty doth belong to us, and to menace us with a total deprivation thereof; and we do alſo fully perſwade our ſelves, that your Majeſty will put this to the ſerious conſideration of your Ministers, who have
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43219:8"/>brought this Proceſs upon the Stage, and perhaps do endeavour to aſſert it's conſiſtency with the Feudal Laws<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that as your Majeſty doubtleſs makes great doubt, to aſſume a Judges part in that proper Cauſe, ſo neither the Sequeſtration of the Fief, nor the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>privation of the ſame can or may conſiſt after that manner, as it it intended againſt us, although we ſhould be undiſputably obliged to that Vaſſallage of the Dukedom of <hi>Schleſwig,</hi> which yet ſaving all due reſpect to your Majeſty, we find our ſo ves neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitated ſolemnly to contradict, except one would preſume to Act by nullities; or by making no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexion upon the Law. And the common Feudal Laws, whereupon likewiſe the ancient unions and Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Agreements, (in caſe any difference as well in Feudal as other matters ſhould ariſe) are uſually grounded, do ſhew, that not only in the total depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of a Fief, but alſo in the Sequeſtration, the hearing of the Cauſe before a Competent Judge ought ſolemnly to preceed, notwithſtanding one would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to aſſert the neceſſiity of a Sequeſtration, in caſe the the parties do ſhew themſelves unwilling; the reaſons whereof nevertheleſs will never be made out by thoſe pretended Machinations.</p>
            <p>Having therefore pondered all the above-mentioned, and ſuch other concomitant circumſtances, we cannot but ſtill keep to our reſolution once deliberately taken and remit that point of our undeſervedly queſtioned Sovereignty over the Dukedom of <hi>Schleſwig,</hi> with all the other abalienated Dignities, Prerogatives, Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and Fortreſſes; as alſo all due and equitable ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43219:8"/>and what elſe can conduce to our future<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, to the place of Congreſs for a general Peace at <hi>Nimvegen,</hi> patiently expecting from God and time, what Concluſion there will be made and come forth about the reſtoring of the Northern Peace, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently alſo of our Rights and Concerns. But we do in the mean while very kindly and inſtantly intreat withal your Majeſty, that out of an inclination to Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and in regard of that deſolate condition, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto we and ours thus undeſervedly ſee our ſelves the more and more reduced, your Majeſty would be pleaſed till then, and till the ſpeedieſt (God grant) enſuing concluſion of a general Peace, to preſerve all peaceable thoughts, and not to preſs upon us any further with the ſaid Inveſtiture, and any other demands; but on the contrary, without delay to recall thot diſconform and miſgrounded Sequeſtration, and not only leave to us the enjoyment of all our Rights and Prerogatives un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſturbed, but alſo to take off the exceeding Contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from our quite exhauſted Subjects, and to reſtore that part of <hi>Stadt</hi> and <hi>Butjadinger-Land</hi> and alſo of the Cuſtoms at <hi>Eltfliet</hi> properly appertaining unto us, and amicably and friendly to interpret this our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable Juſtification and Declaration, with this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance, that as we have in all Points carefully obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that high reſpect due to your Majeſty, ſo likewiſe we have intended to ſay or write nothing, what ſhould tend againſt the ſame. All this is very conſentaneous to equity, and to your Majeſty's inbred Generoſity; and we ſhall be ready for our part every where to praiſe ſuch your Majeſty's kindneſs, and with due
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43219:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>thankfulneſs, and all poſſible ſervices, always acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg the ſame; moſt faithfully recommending withal your Majeſty to God Almighty's Protection.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Dated <hi>Hamborough</hi> 
                  <date>the 16th of <hi>Jan,</hi> 1677.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Majeſties Obſequious Couſin and Brother-in-Law</hi> Chriſtian Albrecht.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:43219:9"/>
            <head>THE EMPEROR'S LETTER to the <hi>Duke of Holſtein.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>
               <hi>LEOPOLD</hi> by the Grace of GOD Elected <hi>Roman</hi>-Emperor.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Serene Duke, &amp;c.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BY theſe we do give to underſtand to your Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, how we are informed, that you have not only for your part approved of thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects which have been made to you by <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventahl</hi> the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Miniſter lately reſiding in our Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial City of <hi>Hamborough,</hi> about certain Levies to be made in Foreign Parts, and are come to a certain con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion with him in that affair; but alſo that your Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection for the promoting of the ſaid Levies hath made uſe of <hi>Kielman</hi> your late Preſident's Moneys, that lie there, and taken thereof the Sum of 200000 <hi>Rix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dollars,</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:43219:10"/>and that your Dilection doth employ in this affair the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Preſident, <hi>K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y,</hi> (who hitherto hath pretended to live there as a private man,) and alſo ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſon named <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And although we do repoſe a far better confidence in your Dilection, than that by ſetting aſide your ſtrict ties and duties towards us, and the whole <hi>Roman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, ſhould thus loſe your ſelf, and by ſuch prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and very much culpable advances, take the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies part, contrary to the publick Statures of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and our imperial Avocatories publiſhed thereupon; yet have we thought good kindly to acquaint, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly to admoniſh you by theſe, that in caſe things ſhould be thus, your Dilection might betimes deſiſt from ſuch enterprizes, and embracing better counſel, comport your ſelf, according to what duty doth require of a Loyal Member of the Empire, to the end, that otherwiſe we may not obliged, to cauſe to be proceeded againſt your Dilection, according to our Imperial Avo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catories; all which is for your Dilections Government; Tendring withal our Imperial Grace and good Will to your Dilection. Dated at our Caſtle at <hi>Lantz</hi> the 6th. of <hi>January</hi> in the year of our Lord 1677. of our Reign in the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire the 19th. in <hi>Hungary</hi> the 22th. and in <hi>Bohemia</hi> the 21th.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>LEOPOLD, V. Leopold William</hi> Count of <hi>Konigſegg.</hi>
               </signed>
               <signed>Ad mandatum Sacrae <hi>Caeſariae,</hi> Majeſtatis proprium, <hi>John Ambroſe Hogell.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:43219:10"/>
            <head>The Duke of <hi>Holſtein's</hi> Anſwer to the afore-going Letter of the Emperor.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Serene, &amp;c.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOur Imperial Maieſties moſt gracious Letter from <hi>Lantz</hi> of the 6th Inſtant, hath been ſome days ago delivered to me by your Imperial Majeſties Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter here reſiding the Lord Baron of <hi>Rondeck,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by me with all the humbleſt reſpects imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; but with an extreme aſtoniſhment I have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by the contents thereof, that your Imperial Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty ſhould have got an information, as if I had not only for my part approved of thoſe projects, which had been made to me by <hi>Graventahl</hi> the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, lately reſiding here in <hi>Hamborough,</hi> about certain Levies to be made in Foreign Parts, and had been come to a certain concluſion with him in that affair; but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that for the promoting of the ſaid Levies; I had made uſe of <hi>Kielman</hi> my late Preſident's Moneys, that lye here, and taken thereof the Sum of 200000 <hi>Rix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dollars,</hi> and that I alſo did employ in this affair the <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh</hi> Preſident <hi>Kleihe,</hi> (who hitherto hath pretended to live here as a private man,) and another perſon like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe named <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>loke;:</hi> And that your Imperial Majeſty moſt graciouſly hath thought good thereupon to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint me therewith, and ſeriouſly to admoniſh me, that in caſe things ſhould be thus, (which yet your Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Majeſty would ſcarce expect from me,) I may betimes deſiſt from ſuch enterprizes, and embracing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43219:11"/>better Counſel, comport my ſelf according to what duty doth require of a Loyal Member of the Empire, to the end, that otherwiſe your Imperial Majeſty may not be obliged to cauſe to be proceeded against me accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to your publiſhed Imperial Avocatories.</p>
            <p>It is true, I cannot promiſe unto my ſelf from your Imperial Majeſties moſt mild, and yet moſt juſt diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, nothing elſe, but that ſuch your Imperial Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties very gracious Letter, although occaſioned by the induſtrious contrivance of ſome envying perſons, who by all ways and means ſeek very watchfully the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion and ruine of my ſelf and my Ducal Houſe, yet to no other end hath been ſent to me, but that your Imperial Majeſty might thereby get a fitter occaſion to diſcover my innocency, and conſequently by your Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Majeſties Authority and higheſt Power to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect me as a Loyal Member and Prince of the Empire, againſt thoſe who have made no conſcience for the ſpace of thoſe 19 months, with a very unworthy treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment undeſervedly to oppreſs me, and of all my Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Dignity to leave me nothing more than bare life: However, when I do call to mind again, in what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner your Imperial Majeſties Requiſitorials concerning me, which were delivered into his Majeſty the King of <hi>Denmark</hi>'s hands, have been by the contrivance of ſome Miniſters, bearing an hatred to me, abuſed ſo far, that they have begun almoſt from that very hour to exhauſt my poor ſubjects as well of <hi>Holſtein</hi> as alſo of <hi>Sleſwig,</hi> with intolerable Contributions, and to render them quite uncapable to contribute ſo much, as they were lawfully bound to do for the upholding my Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly State and Dignity; which proceedings are yet till
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:43219:11"/>this very moment continued, to the utter deſtruction of my Territories, notwithſtanding no further Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Requiſitorials have been inſinuated to me; and though the ſame hath been granted to other States of the Lower Circle of <hi>Saxony</hi> in the point of Quarters: Then have I juſt reaſon to fear, that they likewiſe now under your Imperial Majeſties higheſt Name and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, though againſt your Imperial Majeſties will and intention do go about to colour, and palliate what they newly have ſpun out for the finiſhing of my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditated ruine, and partly have already brought to an execution: All which I have by my former complaints, with all ſubmiſſion repreſented to your Imperial Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and thereby moſt humbly implored your ſpeedy Protection; whereunto alſo I do now refer my ſelf, in hopes your Imperial Majeſty will be pleaſed, not only moſt graciouſly to hear, but alſo ſee them according to your Imperial Clemency forthwith redreſſed.</p>
            <p>Concerning thoſe Accuſations brought before your Imperial Majeſty, and laid home at my door, I ſhould never have Imagined, upon what bottom and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation they could be grounded, unleſs your Imperial Majeſty by the Nomination of certain Perſons had obliged me to a more exact information; whereupon I moſt humbly can aſſure your Imperial Majeſty by a true and faithful Word of a Prince, that I never have hitherto had the leaſt knowledg of thoſe ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Projects, touching the Levies of ſome Forreign Forces, much leſs, that I ſhould have approved of the ſame, or that I ſhould have either directly or indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly with any man in the Worid, dealt or agreed about them. And I can proteſt with Truth it ſelf,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43219:12"/>that neither <hi>Kleyhe</hi> the King of <hi>Sweden</hi>'s Preſident; hath all the during time of his abode here made any Propoſitions to me concerning any Conjunction with Forreign Crowns againſt your Imperial Majeſty, and your high Allies, nor ever offered to perſwade me to any ſuch thing. But this I do declare willingly and freely, that I have cauſed my diſconſolate condition, whereunto I find my ſelf undeſervedly reduced, to be fully repreſented to his Majeſty the King of <hi>Great Brittain.</hi> as Warrant of the Northern Peace, which firſt of all began to bleed and ſuffer on my ſide; and my Requeſts to be made withal, that His ſaid Majeſty would be pleaſed, in reſpect both of that General and Special Warranty taken upon him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning my Sovereignty over the Dukedom of <hi>Sleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wig</hi> lawfully obtained, to procure my Reſtitution, and due Satisfaction; which I have been ſo far from diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owning, that I have contented my ſelf, that the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morials about the ſaid Subject exhibited from time to time by my Deputy, have faithfully been commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Miniſter reſiding in <hi>England.</hi> And I have alſo employed at the Court even the ſame <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>loken</hi> my Covnſellor at Court, whom I did for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt two years imploy at your Imperial Majeſties Court; and have amongſt other Negotiations alſo cauſed my moſt humble Remonſtrations and frequent inſtances by him to be made to your Imperial Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty for my Protection, with theſe certain hopes that he hath behaved himſelf ſo well, that no cauſe is left to put any miſtruſt in him, or to charge him with any ſiniſter and il-grounded accuſations: ſince therefore the aboveſaid foul aſperſions; ſindioudy
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:43219:12"/>contrived by my ill wiſhers, can never be proved, nor laid to my door; the reſt conſequently cannot conſiſt, that for the carrying on of ſuch fictitious Levies, I ſhould have taken and employed the ſaid Sum of 200000 <hi>Rixdollars</hi> belonging to the Heirs of <hi>Kiel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> which monies I do not know in the leaſt if they do lye her or no. Whereas now my Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, and Fictitiouſnes of thoſe Siniſter imputations do ſufficiently appear by the premiſes; ſo can I with all ſubmiſſion aſſure your Imperial Majeſty, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the World ſhall be ever preſſed from me, which may offend and interrupt my Loyal Duties tendered to your Imperial Majeſty, and to the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, and that Devotion which my Anceſtors have with their Princely Blood ſealed up to that Mighty Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> I do therefore again moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly implore your Imperial Majeſty, as the moſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Head of the Empire, that your Imperial Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty would be pleaſed to give no way to all the Suſpicious raiſed againſt me, but rather out of Higheſt Fatherly care to provide for ſuch wayes and means, whereby I as a devoted Co-member of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire may be upheld and freed from all the preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Calamities. Thus longingly I do look for your Imperial Majeſties effectual and gratious Reſolution, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Dated at</hi> Hambourg <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 20 <hi>of</hi> Jan. <hi>Ann.</hi> 1677.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
